Finding aid for the Prison Birth Project records SSC.MS.00728
Sophia Smith Collection
Prison Birth Project records
1993-2018
Sophia Smith Collection
Prison Birth Project
SSC.MS.00728
10 linear feet (5 record cartons, 2 full letter document boxes, 1 half document box, 1 flat box, 4 boxes, 4 flat files)
16 items (10 DVDs, 3 CDs)
136.25 Gigabytes (11,543 digital files)
The Prison Birth Project (2008-2017) worked to "support, encourage, and train currently and formerly incarcerated mothers and trans* parents to become community leaders within a reproductive justice framework." The records include administrative files, program and event planning materials, forms, newsletters and other publications related to midwifery and the Prison Birth Project. Of particular interest are photos and videos of various events, curriculum materials related to Doula training,; and records related to the organization's work on anti-shackling legislation.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveat: Records that identify the names and contact information of Prison Birth Project clients shall be restricted from research use until the year 2033. After that time and until the year 2068, researchers must sign an access agreement, stating they will not reveal the names and personal information of Prison Birth Project clients. Donor files are closed until 2033. Marianne Bullock, Lisa Andrews, and Marisa Pizii, as former Prison Birth Project leaders, may be permitted to access restricted records before they are available for general research.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 14S-49, 15S-78, 16S-19, 2018-S-0005, 2018-S-0048, 2018-S-0049, 2018-S-0059. Accessions were received on the following dates: 2014-07-24, 2015-09-22, 2016-03-03, 2018-02-09, 2018-07-30.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The first accession in the Prison Birth Project Records was donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2014.
Biographical / Historical
The Prison Birth Project was founded in 2008 by Lisa Andrews and Marianne Bullock (Smith College Class of 2014), with the goal of bringing bring doula care to incarcerated women. Lisa was a social justice educator who had supported incarcerated loved ones, and Marianne was a doula who had been incarcerated. In 2011, the Western Massachusetts-based organization transformed itself into a collective, adopting a leadership circle that operated by consensus. Their services included doula and breastfeeding support, childbirth education, and advocacy for incarcerated women and their families.
The organization closed its doors in 2017, citing "large systems of power" and the lack of "the kind of support we need to become the sustainable organization we envision." Among their successes, the Prison Birth Project states that they, "supported over 300 incarcerated people during pregnancy and postpartum and built leadership with over 225 incarcerated parents. Our doulas have attended over 60 births. We helped to pass the landmark Massachusetts legislation ending shackling of pregnant and laboring incarcerated people and monitored successful implementation of new standards." Their projects were distributed to other organizations and practices documented for future use and education.
[sources: PBP Website ]
Related Materials
Related materials may also be found in the following collection:
Women on the Rise Telling HerStory (WORTH) Records
Scope and Contents
The records of the Prison Birth Project are comprised of administrative files such as correspondence, meeting minutes, organizational planning, financial records, grant and fundraising materials, annual reports; as well as materials documenting the organization's events and program planning; worshops and advocacy work for incarcerated women and their families; publicity; publications and ephemera related to midwifery and the Prison Birth Project; as well as website and social media content. Of particular interest are materials related to doula training, breastfeeding and childbirth education, and support groups for incarcerated women and their families; and the records related to the organization's work on anti-shackling legislation. There are also large number of digital photos and video of PBP events. Photos and videos include Doula training, Anti-Shackling training, the annual Mother's Day/Mama's Day, and Solidarity Supper.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Prison births; Bullock, Marianne; Annual reports; correspondence; Leaflets; Newspapers; notebooks; Notes; Pamphlets; Periodicals; Posters; Publications; Works of art; DVD video discs; CDs; Computer media; Electronic records; Prisoners--Legal status, laws, etc.--United States--History--Sources; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Massachusetts; Reproductive health--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Reproductive health advocates; Women prisoners--Massachusetts; Women prisoners -- Abuse of -- United States; Prison reformers -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women prisoners -- Family relationships -- United States; Childbirth--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Prison Birth Project; Bullock, Marianne, AC 2014; Pizii, Marisa; Andrews, Lisa; Johnson, Kenzie; Bullock, Marianne, AC 2014; Pizii, Marisa; Andrews, Lisa; Johnson, Kenzie
- Prison Birth Project records, 1993-2018; 2018-S-0005; 6.5 linear feet (5 record cartons, 1 flat box, 3 flat file folders); 1.8 Gigabytes (1,347 digital files transferred from data CDs, macbook and Google Drive.)
  Scope and Contents
  This addition to the records of the Prison Birth Project (PBP) is comprised of correspondence, event information, grant and financial information, advocacy work, meeting notes, forms, newsletters, posters, and other publications related to midwifery and the Prison Birth Project. Also includes handwritten notes to incarcerated mothers, folders from leadership and activism conferences, and training materials for Prison Birth Project volunteers. Electronic files include Lisa Andrew's computer files related to her work with Prison Birth Project; the archived PBP website and social media; and photos and videos of events.
  Appraisal
  Bank statements, check receipts, and other receipts shredded 2018 August 09, .5 linear feet total.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
  CDs; DVD video discs; Computer media
  - Literature and resources on birth, gender and sexuality, and incarceration, 2003-2017; 10 folders (10 folder) (Box 1)
  - Conference materials and notes, 2009-2017; 16 folders (16 folders) (Box 1)
  - Partner organization files, 2010-2017; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Prison Birth Project general organization information, 2009-2017; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 2)
  - Prison Birth Project forms, 2014-2016; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Board and organization notes and correspondence, 2014-2017; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Event pamphlets, guest lists, and information, 2008-2017; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Mothers Among Us session notes, forms, and reading materials, approximately 2010-2014; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Mothers Among Us writing workshops and essays, 2003-2010; 1 folders (1 folders) (Box 2)
  - Mothers Among Us volunteer coordination, approximately 2008-2014; 1 folders (1 folders) (Box 2)
  - Collages and drawings, approximately 2014; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Client writings, poetry from the Voices from Inside writing group, approximately 2008-2016; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Prison doula information and training, 2008-2017; 9 folders (6 folders and 3 booklets) (Box 3)
  - Childbirth Education program handouts and notes, 2009-2016; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Pregnancy and labor resources, 2002-2016; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 3)
  - Postpartum and parenting resources, 1993-2016; 18 folders (18 folders) (Box 3)
  - Baby onesies with handwritten slogans, approximately 2008-2016; 6 items (6 onesies) (Box 4)
  - Financial and insurance papers, 2010-2018; 9 folders (9 folders) (Box 4)
  - Fundraising and grant papers and correspondence, 2008-2018; 12 folders (12 folders) (Box 4)
  - "Mama's Day Across Bars" cards, 2014-2016; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Reproductive justice advocacy information, 2005-2016; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 5)
  - Leadership development and conference material, 2009-2015; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Anti-shackling and prison reform advocacy papers, 2003-2017; 12 folders (12 folders) (Box 5)
  - Event posters and Prison Birth Project boards, 2011-2017; .5 linear feet (1 flat box) (Box 6)
  - Poster papers from leadership planning meetings for events, future goals, 2011-2017; 3 folders (3 flat files) (Folder 1, Folder 2, Folder 3)
  - Poster papers from client and leadership workshops, 2011-2016; 3 folders (3 flat files) (Folder 1, Folder 2, Folder 3)
  - Video recordings, Prison Birth Project fundraiser, 2012-10-26; 3 items (3 DVDs) (Box 2)
  - Video recording, "Prison Birth Project events", approximately 2010-2016; 1 items (1 DVD) (Box 2)
  - Video recordings, "Prison Birth Project Secret Cafe", 2009-10; 2 items (2 DVDs) (Box 2)
  - Video, "The Motherhood Manifesto" documentary from MomsRising.org, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Video, "Transcending Boundaries: Strengthening Impact" by the Research and Network-Building Project Report, 2011-02; 1 items (1 DVD) (Box 2)
  - "The Prison Birth Project: Lisa's Back up", approximately 2010; 1 items (1 CD); 104 Megabytes (187 digital files) (Box 2)
    Files D include general administrative files such as meeting minutes, event planning, mailing lists, grant materials, publications, and graphics for print and website content. See attached file list for more details.
  - Photos, "Open house", 2010-09-30; 1 items (1 CD); 75 Megabytes (38 files JPG files) (Box 2)
  - Photos, "Prison Birth Project Fall Fundraiser 2012", 1 items (1 CD); 309 Megabytes (106 jpg files) (Box 2)
    General
    Photos by Robin Sidel
  - Lisa Andrews Prison Birth Project computer files, 2008-2010; 238 Megabytes 761 files (documents, spreadsheets, images, and web files)
    Files from Lisa Andrew's computer, including administrative and financial documents, contact lists, program and event planning, meeting minutes, grant and fundraising material, website planning and web content, and images. See file list attached for more detail.
  - Kenzie Johnson's Prison Birth Project photos and video, approximately 2016-2018; 1 Gigabytes (192 jpg files; plus 3 video files)
    Includes primarily photos and a few videos of Prison Birth Project events.
  - Prison Birth Project archived website and social media, captured 2018; 6 website
    The archived website of the Prison Birth Project (http://theprisonbirthproject.org/) was captured after the organization closed, in early 2018. The site includes information about the organization, their work, and partners. In addition, the Prison Birth Project's five social media sites (captured and archived on June 13, 2018): Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, Pinterest, and YouTube include images, video, and publicity for events, and activities,; educational posts, and resources.
    - Prison Birth Project archived website, captured 2018 February; 1 website
    - Prison Birth Project archived Facebook page, captured 2018 June; 1 website
    - Prison Birth Project archived Instagram account, captured 2018 June; 1 website
    - Prison Birth Project archived Pinterest board, captured 2018 June; 1 website
    - Prison Birth Project archived Twitter feed, captured 2018 June; 1 website
    - Prison Birth Project archived YouTube page, captured 2018 June; 1 website
- Marianne Bullock electronic records and images, approximately 2015-2018; Accession 2018-S-0045; 448 Megabytes (419 digital files)
  Marianne Bullock's Prison Birth Project administrative files, including meeting minutes, materials related to anti-shackling legislation), Doula training and curriculum materials, event planning, fundraising and grant materials. In addition there are publications, web and print media planning and content; and images, audio and video of PBP events. See file list for more details. File tpes are primarily Word documents, PDFs, spreadsheets, and JPG images.
  This accession consists entirely of materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
- Lisa Andrews Prison Birth Project computer files, 2011-2018; Accession 2018-S-0048; 3 Gigabytes (3,329 digital files)
  Prison Birth Project administrative files from Lisa Andrew's computer, includes leadership and collective meetings; organizational planning documents; program planning; anti-shackling legislation materials; correspondence; financial and fundraising records; print and web promotional materials; and files related to PBP's closing and legacy project. Images of PBP events include Doula training, Anti-Shackling training, the annual Mother's Day/Mama's Day, and Solidarity Supper.
  This accession consists entirely of materials in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
- Lisa Andrews Prison Birth Project Google Drive and records, 2009-2018; Accession 2018-S-0049; .25 linear feet (1 half document box); 131 Gigabytes (6,448 digital files)
  Lisa Andrews' Google Drive, including a portion of Marisa Pizii's Google Drive, includes general administrative records (staff meetings, advisory board, committee work, and financial materials); event photos and video; Powerpoint presentations; grant and fundraising materials; communication and promotional materials for print media, social media and website; planning documents for programs such as anti-shackling legislation, Doula training workshops, and Mama's Day events. There is also a small amount of paper records that includes donor correspondence, grant information, newsletters and event posters, Prison Birth Project literature, and notes pertaining to both the organization and its decision to close in 2017.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Donated by Lisa Andrews separately from other papers in this collection.
  This accession includes materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  Electronic records
  - Correspondence from donors, approximately 2017; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Grant information, workshops, and letters, 2010-2017; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Prison Birth Project literature and program information, 2013-2016; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Prison Birth Project organization notes, including information on the decision to disband, 2011-2017; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Campaign/event letters, testimonials, donor outreach, 2009-2015; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, sign-up forms, fundraiser invitations, 2012-2016; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, business cards, fundraiser cards, 2009-2016; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Solidarity Supper posters, 2013, 2014; 4 items (4 posters) (Box 6)
  - Lisa Andrews Google Drive records, approximately 2014-2018; 131 Gigabytes (6,448 digital files)
    Lisa Andrews' Google Drive, including a portion of Marisa Pizii's Google Drive, includes general administrative records (staff meetings, advisory board, committee work, and financial materials); event photos and video; Powerpoint presentations; grant and fundraising materials; communication and promotional materials for print media, social media and website; planning documents for programs such as anti-shackling legislation, Doula training workshops, and Mama's Day events. See attached digital file list for details.
    These materials consist entirely of materials feceived from the donor in digital form and are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
    A large amount of duplicate content (mostly photos) and a few confidential files marked to be deleted were removed from this accession before it was backed up to the storage server.
- Prison Birth Project legacy report, 2018; Accession 2018-S-0059; 45 Megabytes (1 PDF file)
  The "Prison Birth Project Legacy Report, 2008-2017: Celebrating 10 Years of Reproductive Justice" is a 103-page document created by the PBP leadership after their closing, includes the history of the organization, with all it's successes and challenges. It was created "with the intent to tell our organization's story in hopes that it can help future activists who take up this important work."